All right.
Okay, hopefully we have a lot to look forward to
as we go into the fall season.
I know that I'm really looking forward to fall a lot.
That's my favorite season of the year.
I really love fall weather.
I love, I'm going to say this,
but I have to say it with a caveat,
I love pumpkin pie.
Please do not everybody give me pumpkin pies.
My wife has told me I have to be careful
when I say I like something
or people end up giving it to me.
So don't feel like you have to give me a pumpkin pie, okay?
But yeah, I really look forward to that.
I really look forward as well
as we get ready for the fall season.
And we're going to be having a lot of students coming back to campus here.
I think all of you who are here for the summer, you know it kind of slows down here, especially in July and August.
It kind of gets a little bit slower.
But we're getting ready now for a new season of college ministry to start up,
especially with undergrad students and grad students coming back to campus here.
And I just want to encourage all of us, kind of looking ahead to that as well.
We're here on this campus for a purpose.
Most of you here in this room today are not college students anymore.
You probably wouldn't be here.
Some of you are.
but you know knowing that just realizing as we go into that fall season part of our calling as a
church together is actually we're here for a purpose of reaching students on this campus and
I love it that we have other life stage ministries in our church now everything from lots of tiny
little babies right now up to people going through every life stage up to retirement I'm so thankful
for that and God's working in our church in many ways that way but I would really encourage us as
well as we look ahead to the fall look forward to new students coming in to our church look
forward to students coming back around campus, even though their parents are going to drive the
wrong way up one-way streets. You know, like still, like let's look forward to that. It's like an
exciting time. The nations gather here. The next generation gathers here. That's part of why we're
here. Like let's look forward to that and say, wow, I get to be used by God to welcome students
into his family. I get to be used by God to pray for those new students who are coming to campus.
I get to be used by God to smile at someone, to welcome someone, to share God's love with someone.
That's an exciting thing.
So let's look forward to that together and see that as a really important reason that we are here on this campus.
Okay, so turn that person you just shared with and say, be excited to meet college students.
Okay, I like that.
You guys said that really strong.
That was good.
I love that.
Yeah, so we're getting ready for a fall season.
And part of that, too, I just want to really quickly celebrate.
We just got back from our youth group retreat over this past week, Sunday through Wednesday.
We had our youth group retreat.
It was a great time.
We had a lot of fun.
And I'm so thankful for our youth group students and seeing the way that they've been seeking God.
They're asking questions.
They're praying for each other.
They're worshiping.
It was a really beautiful time to be together with them.
I'm also really thankful for our youth group leaders who give of themselves so much in serving,
in planning, in praying with the kids, and just investing in that way. It's such a beautiful
and wonderful thing to see people within our church doing that. So can we just real quick
just praise God and celebrate all of them, all of that? Yeah. Yeah. Really great thing. If you see
some of the youth group students, they're mostly like back there hiding in the back row. If you
want, try to track one down after the celebration. Ask them one thing that they learned from their
retreat. I'm sure they'll have lots to share with you. Right, guys? They don't look excited.
They look, they look, I think they're glaring at me right now. Okay. Okay. Let's open to 2 Thessalonians
chapter 2. That's what we're going to be getting into here this morning. And if you remember last
week, we started 2 Thessalonians as part of this Bible short series. We're going through kind of
shorter books of the Bible and books that tend to get less attention than others and kind of
mining those corners of the Bible for treasure and seeing what God will speak to us about this summer.
I think it's been really good. I've been enjoying it a lot. I'm like, man, I probably, I might not
have ever chosen to preach on this chapter, but it's been so good just realizing how much good
stuff there is in these chapters. We started chapter one last week. Pastor Sam preached that
message for us, and we saw Paul writing to this church in Thessalonica and writing to them as
they were going through suffering and hardship and persecution as followers of Jesus, and he's
writing to encourage them. We heard about how Jesus' return gives us hope to face persecution
and live more fully for God, and I hope that was a good message for you to wrestle with and hear
and respond to. Today, we're continuing here into chapter two, and as we get into this, it's another
just really interesting area of the Bible that I think we get to connect with this morning, and
maybe to help us think about that, I don't know how many of you might remember about a year ago
when predictions of the rapture became very, like went viral on social media. Do you guys remember
that at all? Some of you are just like not on social media, and some of you have just forgotten
because so much has happened since then, right? But what happened, especially back at that time,
this happens all the time, but there was this guy, Pastor Joshua Mlakela. I'm not sure if I'm
pronouncing his name right. Here's a picture of him, and he's a pastor in South Africa, and he
predicted Christ's return to be on September 23rd and 24th of last year, of 2025. And so he
predicted this, and it got a lot of attention. He said, I've got a vision from God that Christ is
going to return, the rapture is going to happen, whatever, all that kind of stuff. That's going to
happen September 23rd and 24th, and he got a lot of attention, went all over the place, and a lot
of Christians all over the world took this really seriously, and so that resulted in, you know, people
quit their jobs, people sold their houses, people gave their cars away, and people made millions and
millions of TikTok videos, okay? So this was like all over the place, got a lot of attention,
and then, well, September came and went, and nothing happened. And so then he was like, oh,
no, October. It's October. I just got the month wrong. It's October, okay? So he was like, okay,
okay. October came and went. Okay, nothing happened. Okay, then he waited a little bit.
Then, oh, before the World Cup. World Cup came, and God cares about the World Cup, right? That's
I mean, that's the real message there.
So, you know, all this came out in this,
okay, I don't think he's said too much since then.
It hasn't been that long.
But, you know, all this happens.
And, you know, when these things get out there,
I mean, this was probably a pretty prominent example of this.
But there are people all the time predicting Christ's return.
And, you know, a lot with more or less attention.
This happens a lot.
And I know for many of us,
we likely react to these kinds of things,
maybe with some kind of like hesitation,
some cynicism, like, not really, no, don't care about that kind of thing. But there may be a
little part of us that's like, wait, what if it's real? Could that be true? Does this guy know
something I don't? Did he really see a vision from God? And there's a part of us that might
kind of feel something about that and wonder or worry, feel anxious about these kinds of things.
So this is something we may actually go through ourselves.
And as we look in 2 Thessalonians 2 today,
we're going to see what the Bible says about how we actually should think about Christ's return
and what God wants us to know really clearly about this.
Okay?
So turn to someone next to you and say, God speaks really clearly.
So we're going to see that.
We're going to go ahead and read 2 Thessalonians 2.
I'm going to start with verses 1 through 12, and then we'll read the rest of it after that.
It says this.
Now concerning the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our being gathered together to him,
we ask you, brothers, not to be quickly shaken in mind or alarmed, either by a spirit or a spoken
word or a letter seeming to be from us, to the effect that the day of the Lord has come.
Let no one deceive you in any way, for that day will not come unless the rebellion comes first
and the man of lawlessness is revealed, the son of destruction, who opposes and exalts himself
against every so-called God or object of worship
so that he takes his seat in the temple of God,
proclaiming himself to be God.
Do you not remember that when I was still with you,
I told you these things?
And you know what is restraining him now
so that he may be revealed in his time.
For the mystery of lawlessness is already at work.
Only he who now restrains it will do so
until he is out of the way.
And then the lawless one will be revealed,
whom the Lord Jesus will kill with the breath of his mouth
and bring to nothing by the appearance of his coming.
The coming of the lawless one is by the activity of Satan
with all power and false signs and wonders
and with all wicked deception for those who are perishing
because they refuse to love the truth and so be saved.
Therefore, God sends them a strong delusion
so that they may believe what is false
in order that all may be condemned
who did not believe the truth
but had pleasure in unrighteousness.
We'll pause there.
Let's pray once more together.
God, we invite you to speak to us today.
We know, Lord, that you want to speak clearly.
You want to give us direction.
You want to guide us, Lord,
in how we live the life that you have given to us, Lord,
and also how we think about the things to come
that will be in the future.
God, you want to show us your will,
your plan, your heart.
You want to tell us enough, God,
that we will know how to live in this present world.
So guide us, speak to us, lead us, God.
We pray this day would be both challenging
and convicting for us, God, as we look into your word. Thank you, God. It's in Jesus' name that we
pray. Amen. Amen. Okay, so as we look at this chapter, I'm just guessing that for many of us,
this might be the kind of chapter that when it comes up in our Bible reading plan and we read it,
we might be like, okay, hope there's something easier to understand tomorrow. Like, what is all
of this stuff? It'd be nice if there's something a little more encouraging in here. This seems kind
of overwhelming. You know, maybe we kind of react to a passage like this in that way. And so how do
we approach a passage like this? You know, just a couple introductory comments. Paul is addressing
here a topic known as the end times. It's what theologians call eschatology. It's a study of
how God is going to bring his plan for creation to completion. And evidently, the believers in
Thessalonica, they have been writing to Paul, they wrote a letter to him, and they're asking him some
questions about this. So, last week, we heard about how they're facing persecution, right?
They're going through hardship and difficulty, and like Pastor Sam shared with those, that Paul
was trying to give some perspective to them, some hope, some encouragement for them to live fully
for Christ. Well, now here, they're bringing up another issue of saying, like, well, how are we
supposed to think about this end times stuff and some specific things we'll talk about today.
And so we're going to look at this a little bit and just understand when we say end times,
we're not talking about just like one event. We're talking about a whole series of events
of how God is going to bring his plan to completion. And you might, as you look through
the Bible or you read different things or hear different people teach about this, you'll hear
people talk about things like the day of the Lord, like the rapture, like the great tribulation,
final judgment, Armageddon, the millennial reign of Christ, all these kinds of things. There are
tons of terms and topics that all fall under this area of the end times or of eschatology.
And you may be familiar with some passages in like the book of Revelation or Daniel chapter 7 to 9
or Matthew 24 and 25 where Jesus talks about this and many other places across scripture
all addressing this topic that for many of us feels kind of overwhelming and hard to understand.
And so as we look into this here today, I think for many of us, we tend toward two extremes
of how we respond to this kind of thing in Scripture, or even when we hear it talked
about just in the world today.
Two extremes of that, and I think one extreme of that would be those who really think about
the end times very obsessively.
And a lot of times this looks like things like trying to predict the timing of Christ's
return, or maybe of even getting into things like accusing certain political leaders or things of
like, are you the antichrist? Are you the antichrist? That kind of stuff. And then maybe like ruminating
over like numerology and typology in the Bible and trying to calculate stuff and figure things
out. That's one way people might tend to respond to this topic. And, you know, from looking at that,
I just want to share up front, I think, you know, Jesus gave a really great teaching when he said
a tree is known by its fruit. And when we look at this, what fruit do we see of this kind of
response to this topic? I think for me, when I see the fruits of this kind of response, a lot of
times what I observe is fear. I observe suspicion and kind of like, yeah, that tendency to point
fingers. I observe a lot of division that that brings. And also, a lot of times it brings kind
of a retreat from the world that we live in, a retreat from our calling in the world to kind of
be separated from in an unhealthy way. So there's some of those things like, okay, like that's maybe
one extreme of it. The other extreme that I think I see is people who just don't think about the end
times or Christ's return at all, ever. Just like, oh, that's kind of weird. Don't want to think about
that kind of stuff. I got enough to do right in front of me, and like, why would I want to think
anything about that? You know, what's that have to do with me? And I think that has its own kind
of fruit, if you will. I think the fruit of that kind of mindset, saying I'm just not going to think
about this at all, a lot of times that brings with it a very temporary mindset. I'm only thinking
about the here and now. I'm not thinking about where I'm going. It brings, I think, with that
an absence of eternal hope, forgetting what it is that Christ has planned for us, forgetting how
God is going to restore all things and not realizing that's where our real hope lies. It can
make us oblivious to the spiritual world and the reality that's actually out there that we live
in the midst of. So that's also not where we want to go. Now, we can't hope to cover this entire topic
of the end times here today. Maybe we need to do that sometime in the future. That's just a massive
and very hard to understand area of Bible and theology. But today, in this passage, Paul gives
us some really direct guidance and information that I think is actually sufficient to help us
in a lot of these concerns or questions that we might have that might get brought up as we live
the Christian life in the world today. And the first big area that Paul wants to talk to us
about here today is the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ. This is the area that we get to focus on
today. The coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, what's that going to be like? What should we expect?
what should we know about it, okay? Now, if you do any reading on this or if you see people talking
about this, you'll probably come across people using this Greek word parousia. So I just want
to introduce that to you. It's a Greek word that simply means to come or to arrive, to be present
in a space or a situation. And if you see, like, that's the word here where it says the coming of
our Lord Jesus Christ. That word coming, arrival, appearing, that is this word. And so if you hear
people talking about this, they'll talk about the parousia, and that means the return of Christ to
the world, Christ's second coming. And so Paul's talking here about Jesus' return to judge the
world and to gather all who are in Christ to himself. That's what we're talking about here
today. And what does he specifically advise the church as they've written to him? He says,
do not be shaken, alarmed, or deceived. Okay, and that's what he wants for them. He says,
I don't want you to be shaken, alarmed, or deceived as you think about or as you hear about
some of these things related to this topic. Now, he then goes on and says a few specific things.
He says, you know, don't let this happen by a spirit. Now, that likely means that in the
gathering of the church, somebody has claimed to give a prophecy saying something about this,
saying maybe Christ has already returned. We see it as we read through this passage. That's
one way. He goes, so not by a spirit, also by a spoken word. That will be somebody actually standing
up in the gathering of the church and teaching something, saying Christ is going to return this
way, or Christ has already returned this way, not as a prophecy, but as a teaching. Or he also says
by a letter seeming to be from us. So evidently, there's somebody or maybe multiple people who
knows who have actually written a letter to the church fraudulently claiming to be from Paul
and saying, Christ has already returned.
He says, don't let that fool you either.
These were false teachings intended to lead the church astray
to believe, quote, the day of the Lord has come.
Well, that means Christ has already returned.
He's already here.
And now think about this church.
Think about how they would respond to this.
They're going through persecution.
They're suffering for their faith.
They're waiting on the hope of Christ's return
and what he will do to bring them to eternal salvation.
They're waiting on that.
And now somebody's come along and told them
the day of the Lord has come already.
Jesus is already here.
And then they're thinking, wait, where?
He's here?
Where is he?
Like what, how could we have missed him?
I thought we weren't gonna miss him.
I thought we were gonna see him.
I thought we were gonna know him.
And so do we need to go find him somewhere?
Is he over in Spain?
Is he in Egypt? Like, where is he? Where are we supposed to go? Like, can you imagine for people
suffering, struggling in their faith, waiting on Christ's return, and then, wait, he's coming,
we don't know it? This by itself is probably a terrifying and anxiety-inducing thought for them,
right? And so I think as we recognize this situation and what's going on here, I think we
should also recognize that while this may feel distant to us, that this is actually relevant
for us today. And we should want to understand this because it does affect our spiritual lives
even as we live in today's world. One thing that's really helpful to understand is every
generation of Christians who's gone before us all have believed that Christ will return in their
lifetime. Everyone has thought that. And so here today, we live in our present world. We look around
us. We see, man, there's wars and rumors of wars. There's famines. There's all this kind of stuff.
There's wickedness. Man, maybe Christ is coming now. And what do we do with those thoughts,
with those questions, with that information? What has happened a lot also throughout history
is people trying to predict these things.
I shared one example of you earlier
that happened just last year.
I'll give you just a couple more here
just so you see kind of a breadth of them.
There's another guy named Harold Camping.
He was the president of the Family Radio Network.
This is a network of Christian radio stations
that had broad distribution.
And he predicted back in the 1990s,
he predicted that Christ would return
on September 6th, 1994.
And then that date came and went.
And so then later on, he predicted again
for May 21st, 2011, then October 21st, 2011, and I guess he's kind of done now. Another one, this
doesn't just happen in the U.S., although I feel like American Christians do this a lot, but another
example is a guy named Hongmin Chen. He was from the Taiwanese God's Salvation Church. It was a
church he led, and he felt he had received a vision from God, and so he told all of his followers from
his church to move from Taiwan to Texas, because evidently God still works in the U.S. mainly.
And so they all move to this town in Texas, and he tells them God is going to put a broadcast on
local channel 18 on TV, and he's going to do it on March 25th, 1998. And then after the broadcast
on March 25th, then Jesus is going to return on March 31st in a flying saucer. And that's how
that's going to happen. And, I mean, this whole church up and moved and believed them and followed,
right? So these things happen, right? And as we look at these kinds of things, I mean, partly,
I just want to say up front, I think we should probably take Jesus at his word when he said
that nobody will know the day or the hour, right? Matthew 24, Mark 13, you can look up those verses,
okay? Jesus says this very clearly, nobody's going to know the day or the hour.
Now, why are people trying to predict this?
It has to do with hope.
We're made to hope in something.
We place, all of us, all of us place our hope in something.
And at the very least, I could say for these believers,
they're placing their hope in the return of Christ.
Now, I will also say, as kind of the other side of that coin,
is that if Jesus says
nobody's going to know
the day or the hour
if somebody says
I've had a vision from God
telling me the day and the hour
that would mean that God
is contradicting the words of Jesus
pretty sure that doesn't happen
you can know immediately
that's not real
and there are others
who try to figure this out
with numerology
with patterns in the Bible
with stuff like that
and again Jesus said
nobody's going to know
the day or the hour
if somebody says
they know the day or the hour
the one thing you can be certain
is it's not that day or that hour
that's all you can do you know that okay great we're good there's this desire to know with
certainty when that hope will arrive and I think that again we should be careful of this we should
not Paul is really concerned here that people are being shaken alarmed deceived by all of this stuff
so we should know enough to be careful of that but I have a feeling for many of us we probably
hear stuff like this, and okay, yeah, I'm not being deceived by that. I'm not being distracted
by that. I don't care about that at all. If somebody says that they know when Jesus is
returning, I'm not going to listen to them. I don't care. I'm going to move on with my life.
Okay, great. We should not fall prey to that stuff. But on the other side of that, again, notice
all of this has to do with hope. And for some of us, maybe we're not attaching ourselves so much
to a certain date, certain time, a certain way that Christ is going to return. We're not watching
for that flying saucer. But what else do we fixate our hope on? I think for a lot of us, this is the
direction we go astray. Knowing people in our church, I think the vast majority of us here
probably don't get too much into the Jesus return predictions, but we put our hope in other
things. And there are a lot of just normal things of life, but we get really attached to these
things. It can be something as simple as, what will be the outcome of the next election?
Why? Because there's a level of hope that we're placing in that outcome. When will the next
stock market crash happen? How will it affect my retirement? When will the next housing market
crash happen? Because I want to buy a house. Who is going to win the national championship this year?
really important stuff
again
God cares about the world cup
and the national football championship
where will I get into college
where will I get into grad school
where will I get that next job
because there's a hope
attached to these things
now it's not wrong
to look forward to
to pursue
to desire certain things
in life
that's not what I'm saying
but are we putting so much hope
in these things
to the neglect of our eternal hope in Christ
that we simply don't pay much attention at all
to the fact that Jesus is going to return.
And when he returns,
he is going to bring judgment upon the sin of the world.
He is going to make all things new.
He is going to lead us into that eternal salvation with God.
Like, do our hearts resonate with that
and say, God, I want that, I hope for that, I long for that, I'm pursuing that, that's why I live my
life, that's why I do what I do, that's the direction I want to go in, that is what I am
waiting for, I'm praying and expecting Christ's return, I want to believe that he is going to come
and take me and my spiritual family home, I am looking for that, waiting for that, or
man, I would just kill for a lower mortgage rate, where is our hope? And again, for all the, for all
I think it is misguided and even dangerous to make these predictions about the timing of Christ's
return, at least their hope is in that direction. That's more than maybe some of us actually could
say if we're honest this morning. And so we should wrestle with these things. And so it's not that
thinking about the return of Christ or even other future events is bad, but how we do it matters.
And again, Paul here, he gives some specific guidance that is enough for us to know how to
respond and deal with these things, okay? So first of all, we should realize this is not the first
time Paul's talking to them about these things. Verse 5 tells us that Paul taught about the day
of the Lord in person when he was with them in Thessalonica, okay? So he's already told them in
person all these things, he said. But then we also see his previous letter, 1 Thessalonians,
that he wrote about Christ's return in that letter. So you can go back. I'm not going to
read the whole passage, but you can read 1 Thessalonians 4.13 to 5.11. He gives some other
teaching about that, just to remind them. I taught you in person. I sent you another letter about this.
Now they have questions, and he's responding to those questions here today. And from this, there
are two things we can know for certain and that are going to be really clear and obvious that help us
know how to respond. When people say, oh, Christ's returning over there. Maybe it's this time. There
are two things we can know for certain that I think we can rest upon here this morning from
this passage. The first of those is that the man of lawlessness will come first. The man of
lawlessness will come first. Who is this man of lawlessness? In this passage, he's called the son
of destruction, and he is empowered by Satan. So this is not Satan. This is a human empowered by
Satan, and this person is empowered to use false signs and wonders to deceive those who refuse the
truth and reject God. Okay, that's who this man of lawlessness is. Along with him will come greater
rebellion. So it's not just one individual, but there will be greater rebellion coming along with
this person. And Paul writes about this elsewhere in 2 Timothy 3 as well. He says,
Indeed, all those who desire to live a godly life in Christ Jesus will be persecuted,
while evil people and imposters will go on from bad to worse, deceiving and being deceived.
So this is what's going to happen.
This man of lawlessness will come, additional rebellion will come along with him,
and what will happen is that he will take his seat in the temple of God
and proclaim himself to be God.
So when Jesus talks in Mark 13, 14 about the abomination of desolation,
I think this is what he's talking about.
So this is pretty clear stuff.
And what we should take away from this is that this description is so clear
that if it happens, it will be obvious to those who are in Christ. We'll be able to see it, and
we won't be wondering, wait, did Jesus return over there? Did something happen? Like, we won't be,
like, uncertain and confused about it. It'll be really clear. Someone sitting on the throne of
the temple saying, I'm God. Pretty clear, right? So, we will know when this happens. And this is
so clear, that I think also just as predicting timing of Christ's return, I think it's also wise
to be hesitant about pointing fingers at people and saying that somebody is the man of lawlessness
or the antichrist. It's just another area I think we should maybe be especially careful of. I remember
back maybe 15 years ago or so, a really prominent televangelist on his TV broadcast saying that
a combination of President Barack Obama at the time and Pope Francis were the head of government
and the religious head that were together going to be this man of lawlessness and usher in this
whatever. And I was like, man, I think those kinds of speculations do not help anybody.
I think they also go well beyond what the text here shows us is clearly true, is obvious.
And I think one of my big issues with that,
and I say this because we're not listening
to maybe that guy anymore.
In fact, he passed away since then.
But there's so much in today's world,
like on YouTube, on TikTok, on Instagram.
Messages about all kinds of different stuff.
People giving prophecies about stuff.
People teaching things from scripture
that are just really off base.
All this kind of stuff.
And one of my big issues with this
is that when something's shown to be clearly wrong,
you rarely see anybody repent for it.
Personally, I think like that televangelist I mentioned,
he should have repented,
saying, no, it turns out it wasn't Barack Obama or Pope Francis.
Turns out that didn't happen.
Same thing with some of these predictions of the rapture things.
If it doesn't happen, you should repent.
Say, I was wrong.
I'm not going to make those kind of statements again.
So that's something to look for.
When you're thinking about, who do I listen to?
Should I listen to this person on YouTube?
Should I listen to this person on TikTok?
talk? Should I follow this person's teachings? Observe their teaching, their way of life. And
when they say something that's wrong, that's demonstrably wrong, do they repent and correct
it publicly? That's a sign of integrity. And if somebody's not, if you don't observe that in
somebody, then you should not listen to them. You should not consider them to be a valid teacher or
spiritual leader. Okay, I'm sharing that because that's the world we live in today. And back at this
time they were dealing with the same kinds of things. So Paul says, hey, very clearly, this man
of lawlessness, he's going to show up first. You're going to be able to identify him. He's going to be
the guy on the throne in the temple saying he's God. That's how you're going to identify him, right?
And then he's currently being restrained, but he's going to be released and revealed at the right
time. And when he does, well, then the second thing we can know for certain is going to happen.
First thing was the man of lawlessness will come first.
Second thing we can know for certain,
which I think is pretty good news,
is Jesus will kill him and bring him to nothing.
Good job, Jesus.
It says he will kill him by the breath of his mouth.
That's some bad breath.
Powerful.
Had a lot of altoids or something, I don't know.
But he will kill him by the breath of his mouth.
That word breath, just so you know,
the word breath, translated breath here is pneuma.
It's the same word for spirit.
And think about like John chapter 20, Jesus breathed on his disciples and said, receive the
Holy Spirit. So he says he killed him with the breath of his mouth. That is with the power of
the Holy Spirit. You know, he put him to death. He punished him with death. Again, this is a human
empowered by Satan. He's now receiving judgment from Christ. And it's not just that he killed
him with the power of the Holy Spirit. It says he brings him to nothing by the appearance of his
coming. So just by showing up, okay? Like if I was speaking to Pastor Josh, I'd be like, Pastor Josh,
you know when like the wrestlers come in at WrestleMania and they come out with their theme
song and they show up and everybody's like, you know, like, man, times a million or something,
okay? Jesus appears and just his appearing, his showing up, this guy collapses. He's brought to
nothing, right? As Christians, I think God wants us to be aware of these spiritual realities and
he wants us to have enough information about his plans so that we can know what is true and false
and what to expect. And what I think we can take away from this here is that God does not want us
to be afraid and he doesn't want us to be led astray. And we should know, just as a verse shared
with you earlier from 2 Timothy, there will be real trials. There will be real tribulations.
There will be persecution. There will be these hardships as we follow Jesus, but Jesus will be
victorious because the one who spoke the whole universe into being and the one who died and rose
again and won victory over sin and death, he is going to be victorious. He is going to win this
fight. And we have to know this. We should know this with such confidence. I think for many of us,
we just don't know how to think about these end times things we see in the Bible.
So maybe we imagine it's something like a Marvel movie.
And like we think, okay, early in the movie, the hero or the heroes,
they're going to have a fight with this bad guy.
And early in the movie, the bad guy is going to win.
And then they're going to have to go and retreat and get their stuff together.
And there's going to be a personality conflict.
And they're going to have to deal with this.
And then they're going to come back.
And then there's going to be a final battle.
And at the final battle, it's going to be tough.
It's going to be close.
We're not sure who's going to win, but eventually the heroes win just by the smallest hairbreadth, right?
The heroes win.
And this is not going to be like that.
This is not going to be like that.
It is not a close fight.
Jesus is going to win decisively in this fight.
We do not need to fear.
I think all of this that I'm sharing about with you here today is really important for us.
It is important because ultimately, I mean, again, there's information flying around,
people teaching, prophesying, claiming different things.
We need to know what to do with that.
But I do think we need to be challenged about where our hope lies
and what we're pursuing and even what we're falling maybe into believing that we shouldn't.
This stuff can be dangerous.
if you can be led astray by a false prophet predicting the timing of Christ's return,
I think you're vulnerable to being led astray by this man of lawlessness.
He's going to come with false signs and wonders.
If you will fall victim to someone on TikTok saying it's going to be on this date, this hour,
I think you're vulnerable to being led astray.
And we should pay attention to that.
We should be careful of that.
We should know enough of the scriptures that we don't fall into that.
That's dangerous.
On the other side of that, if we're so focused on the temporary things of this world
that we've totally forgotten that Jesus will return,
we don't even care if he returns because our life here seems pretty good
and we don't need him to come back anyway,
well, then it's pretty easy for us to be led astray into false and temporary hopes
that will lead us away from a life of close relationship with God our Father,
His Son Jesus, and His Spirit who lives in us.
We should be aware of these things and careful with these things.
And so Paul, he's trying to make all that really clear.
He says, don't be shaken.
Don't be alarmed.
Don't be deceived.
Don't let these things happen to you.
Don't fall into that kind of stuff.
But then at the end of the chapter, he really wants to encourage them.
And so let's read the last few verses here.
verse 13 to 17 says this, but we ought always to give thanks to God for you, brothers beloved by
the Lord, because God chose you as the first fruits to be saved through sanctification by the spirit
and belief in the truth. To this he called you through our gospel so that you may obtain the
glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. So then, brothers, stand firm and hold to the traditions that you
were taught by us, either by our spoken word or by our letter. Now may our Lord Jesus Christ himself
and God our Father who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace,
comfort your hearts and establish them in every good work and word. Amen. As we look at these last
few verses here, what you may notice is that there's that transition word at the beginning
of verse 13, but. But we ought always to give thanks to God for you. This is kind of a turning
point. It's a contrasting point. He's saying, I'm so thankful for you, my dear brothers and sisters.
I'm so thankful for you because you're not going the direction of all that stuff that we just
talked about. I'm so thankful because you're living in the truth. You're not falling into
that. You're standing firm even though you're under persecution. You're not falling into all
of that. You are going a way of genuine faith. And so this is what Paul wants to tell them at
the end of this, he wants them to stand firm. Stand firm, my brothers and sisters, right? Paul knows
that he is speaking to Christians who may have been a bit rattled by everything that they're
going through. They've been facing persecution. They're really suffering for their faith in Christ,
and now they're wondering, might we have missed Christ's return altogether? They may be a bit
shaken up by all these things they're going through. Some of us here today, maybe you feel
a bit shaken up, even in your faith, because of some things you've been going through in life.
Paul sees that in the church, and he wants to encourage them. So I want to share this all
with you as an encouragement as well. The first thing he really wants them to do is to remember
that you are beloved and chosen. That's what we can hold on to, remember that you are beloved
and chosen. And because God has chosen you, he now wants to lovingly build you up to be the person
in Christ that he has made you to be and that he's redeemed you to be. He wants to build you up in
that. Notice it says this is happening because God chose you as the first fruits to be saved through
sanctification by the Spirit and belief in the truth. Because God has chosen you, he is going
to sanctify you, and he wants to lead you into the truth that is going to enable you to stand firm.
These are really important things, and this is something I just want to give, again, as an
encouragement to some of us that maybe we just, maybe it doesn't feel very pleasant to us,
really embrace the sanctifying work of God in your life. If He has chosen you, if He loves you,
He loves you enough to try to set you free from things that are holding you back,
to try to correct maybe some false beliefs you have with the truth, to try to build you up in
every way. And so right now, as we go through life, this is a lifelong journey of sanctification.
Look in your life. Ask God. God, show me. I'm your beloved child, so in your love, God, show me if
there's a way that I'm going off track. In love, God, show me if there's an area where my character
is immature. God, show me if there's an area where I'm living in unbelief and not trusting you. God,
show me and sanctify me, purify me, because God in his love, because he has chosen us, he wants
to build us up in that. And while it might not feel good going through that time, this will
produce a harvest of righteousness in us. And so embrace that. Say, God, I'm your chosen, beloved
child. God, build me up just as your word says that you will do. Second thing it says here as an
encouragement is you will obtain the glory of our Lord. You will obtain the glory of our Lord.
How does that feel when you hear that? I think for a lot of us, we feel a little hesitant about
that. I mean, it sounds something, it should be happy. Yeah. I've been obtained the glory of our
Lord. Yeah. I think for a lot of us, it's a little bit like, I don't know about that. That feels a
little bit wrong. It feels like maybe that I shouldn't want that or I shouldn't get that.
I had a friend when I was in high school, and he was an extraordinarily talented musician.
And so all through high school, he took just every music class that he could be in, and then he took
whatever other classes that were easy so he could spend more time on music. So he didn't take any
high-level classes or anything. He just took the bare minimum that he had to take, get through high
school, and graduate. Senior year rolls around, and in my high school, we didn't have a valedictorian.
and we had an academic top 10.
That's what they did instead.
And they announced the academic top 10.
And who's in the academic top 10?
My friend.
And it was actually all my other friends too.
I wasn't in there
because I was a bad student in high school.
But me and all my friends,
we took all the APs, the honors classes,
all that kind of stuff.
And many of my friends,
they were in that academic top 10.
And then there's this guy.
And I remember they got him up at assembly
and had him stand up there
and he looked so embarrassed.
He was like, and he actually came up to me.
I mean, this is a great guy, one of the most genuine guys I've ever met.
He came up to me after they announced it, and he said, Pete, I'm so sorry.
I feel like I took your spot, bro.
And I was like, don't worry, my GPA is not that good.
But he got all A's because he took classes that were fairly easy and didn't require a lot,
and so he got all A's.
And afterward, he was like, man, I feel like I didn't deserve this.
I feel like I took somebody else's spot.
Like, this seems wrong.
Like, why am I getting this attention?
And then, I mean, don't worry, things worked out really well for him.
He was a touring musician for a long time,
and now he actually works for American Idol, like, coaching the acts.
So he's doing pretty well.
But I share this because, you know, we need to understand,
nobody earns the grace of God.
Nobody earns the grace of God.
And to participate in the glory of Christ is pure grace.
Okay?
Like, this is what it says.
To this he called you through our gospel.
Okay, that means this is a gospel thing. Nobody's going to earn it anyway. Nobody's worthy of it
anyway except Christ alone. But why did Jesus go to the cross? Why did he suffer and die on our
behalf? Why did he go through that pain, that shame, that rejection? Why did all of that happen?
It's so that, I mean, Philippians 2 says, for the joy set before him he endured the cross. What is
that joy? The joy of getting laid in a tomb? The joy of rising again and just going and hanging out
with God in eternity forever by themselves? No, the joy set before him is that his lost brothers
and sisters, God's lost children, will be gathered back to himself in glory. And by you being included
in that glory does not mean that somebody else lost their spot. His glory is forever and ever.
it is infinite, there is no limit to the glory that he has, and the more people that are in that
glory, the more that it magnifies the worthiness of our Savior. So here, there's no reason to feel
negatively, to feel hesitant, to feel, oh, I'm so unworthy. Like, yes, we're unworthy, but let the joy
come to you that it is by grace and you didn't earn it. We need to embrace and say, wow, this is a
real hope. Like, think about this, especially for maybe here, maybe our lives are just too good and
too easy. But imagine for these first century believers, they're being persecuted. They're
afraid of whether they're going to miss the return of Christ. They're wondering if their property is
going to get confiscated. They're wondering if they're going to survive the week. They're wondering
these things and they need a real hope to hold on to and to say that you will obtain the glory of
our Lord means to them whatever they go through in this life, it is worth it. And so let's hold on
to that same hope and know that hope is not just for them. We may look at them and say, wow, it looks
like they earned theirs. They went through persecution, suffering, all that. Maybe they
earned their spot. But no, just as for us is for them. It is only by the grace and mercy of God.
And we all get to share in that glory just the same. And after all of that, Paul says, stand
firm and hold to the traditions. Stand firm and hold to the traditions. I don't know what you think
about when you hear the word tradition. I think for some people, tradition holds a sense of kind
of nobility, honor, respect, something enduring, something good. I think in the world today, it's
maybe more likely that we might feel like, oh, tradition, that's old, that's stale. That's for
another time, another place. I'm more modern than that. I've discovered new ways. I want to do my
own way. I don't want to go the traditional route. But here, when we hear this, to hold to the
traditions, what we should feel is a sense that we're part of something bigger than ourselves.
That's what we should feel. That when we participate in all these things of the Christian
life that we do, that we actually stand together with those who have confessed Christ over the
centuries, over the millennia, that we stand with those who have suffered and even given their lives
for their faith. We're part of something much bigger than ourselves. And I don't know how aware
we are, of like when we just live our Christian lives, how much of that connection, that unity,
that sense of something greater really should permeate everything that we do. Like think about
for a second, here's a picture of a baptistry. This is in Laodicea. So one of the early churches
around the same time, right? Same area as this church in Thessalonica. And this is a baptistry
there. It's made in the shape of a cross. This dates from sometime in the 300s. And I show this
picture, just think about this with me. I mean, this, when it was first used, this would have been
a closed building, probably would have been dark. And imagine somebody going to get baptized
in those early centuries. And that person going to get baptized knows when they step down into
that baptismal pool that they are truly dying with Christ. They know that to believe in Christ,
to devote their lives to him,
to say, I belong to him.
He died and rose again for me,
and now they're gonna devote themselves to him
and no other.
They knew that that came with a cost.
They knew they might be killed.
They knew they might be beaten.
They knew they might be separated from their family.
They knew they might be betrayed
by their closest friends.
They knew they might lose everything
for following Christ.
And you know, when they did that,
when they stepped down into that pool,
they said something very similar to the Apostles' Creed
that we read at the beginning of our celebrations.
And they would step down into that pool.
They would say, I believe in God,
the Father Almighty,
maker of heaven and earth.
I believe in Jesus Christ,
his only Son, our Lord.
I believe.
And they would rest their lives upon it.
And so when we gather,
when we do the things we do,
when we lift up songs of worship,
when we pray,
when we gather on Sunday mornings,
when we minister to one another in prayer,
when we read the word together,
when we do all of these things, can we have a sense it's not just about us here and now. We're
part of something greater than ourselves. Let's join in that tradition of believers through the
centuries, through the millennia, who have given their lives to Christ. In fact, they're staked
their lives and their eternal hope upon him. That's what all of this is about. Stand firm.
We need to have courage because while there is this certainty of eternal hope that we have,
we also don't know when that rebellion will come.
We don't know when that man of lawlessness will come.
Will it be in our generation?
Will it be in another?
We don't know.
But we always need to be ready for it.
So stand firm.
And Paul ends this chapter with a prayer for the Thessalonian church.
Verse 16 and 17 again,
Now may our Lord Jesus Christ himself and God our Father,
who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace,
Comfort your hearts and establish them in every good work and word.
Paul is praying here in a way to remind the believers not to focus just on their situation,
but to root their hope, to root their prayers in God and who his character is.
This is about the Lord Jesus, God our Father.
He gave us eternal comfort and hope and grace.
He did all these things for us.
and he says, he prays, comfort your hearts and establish them. So, you know, that word establish,
it means strengthen. Strengthen them for the good work, the good word that the Lord has entrusted
to you. And here as we close this out, even as we hear this prayer, as a prayer prayed for us,
the church, can we think about and recognize there is a good work that the Lord has prepared for each
of us to do. Probably not just one good work, probably many good works, many good words to
share about Christ and what he has done. And so let's think about, is there a good work for the
Lord that maybe you've grown weary of doing? I know many of us face that. There are times I face
that. I'm like, God, I'm tired. I'm just tired. I don't know how to go on. Paul prays here for the
church. We can take this as a prayer for ourselves. Be strengthened. Be established. Be strong in the
Lord. Is there a good work the Lord has called you to that maybe you're avoiding? Maybe God showed
you, spoke to you, challenged you, invited you. For whatever reason, you've been avoiding that
call of Christ on your life. Is there a good work for the Lord that maybe you feel inadequate for?
if you feel inadequate that's good
you're in good company
you're right there with everyone
who said yes to the Lord before you
feeling inadequate is not a reason
to not follow God's call
or not do the work he's called you to
all of us are inadequate
have you been wandering away because of that
here as we read this prayer
stand firm
pray, trust the Lord
to empower you
a lot of things we can say about the end times
in the New Testament,
but I'll maybe wrap up a little bit
with this verse here
that Jesus himself said in Mark 13, 33.
Be on guard.
Keep awake,
for you do not know
when the time will come.
We don't need to make predictions.
We don't need to try to figure it out
by this verse and that verse
and this number and that measurement
and all this kind of stuff.
We don't need to wait
for a vision for the Lord.
Be on guard.
Keep awake.
Stand firm.
We don't know when the time will come.
As one thing for today, don't be distracted or deceived.
Stand firm as we wait for Christ's return.
Don't be distracted or deceived.
Pastor Sam mentioned last week that there are people in the world today
who are living under persecution.
And for myself, I think I find it encouraging, challenging, inspiring,
and it moves me to pray when I hear the stories of people
who are suffering for their faith in the world today.
I'd like to close with just sharing one example of that with you.
And this picture is of a woman named Helen Burhain, and she's from Eritrea.
She's a gospel singer.
And if you know about Eritrea, it's a country in Africa where there is quite a bit of persecution against Christians.
I'll share a little bit of her story with you.
Helen placed her faith in Jesus at eight years old while her parents were political prisoners.
By the age of 14, she began writing her own worship music, and at 18, she began preaching the gospel in the streets of her city.
In 2002, so this was happening a little while ago,
some laws were passed in Eritrea against evangelism.
And in 2004, the government closed Helen's church that she was part of,
and they were not allowed to gather together anymore in person.
Helen saw a need there, and so she decided to record a CD.
People used CDs back then.
She decided to record a CD of gospel music
so that her church members could still worship the Lord at home,
even while they weren't able to meet together in person.
And this was found out, and so Helen was arrested shortly after the release of that CD as it was distributed.
She was imprisoned for 32 months at the Mai Serwa prison in a steel shipping container that was her cell in the desert heat.
She was chained to the wall and given minimal food, no bathroom to use.
The guards beat her and told her that if she would just deny her faith and sign a document saying that she denied Christ,
then she could be set free, but she refused to do so. Even while the guards were beating her with
rods, Helen continued to sing songs of worship and to lift her eyes to the Lord. Eventually, the guards
realized that she would not deny her faith in Christ and that she was near death, and so they
released her and sent her home to die. But her family found her, and she fled to Sudan, and then
she received asylum in Denmark, where she continues to worship and serve the Lord today.
I share this story just partly as just awareness. I think it's important for us to be aware
of what's going on in the world, aware of the sufferings of our brothers and sisters in Christ.
But I think it's also a good encouragement to us to remember the things we read about in
Scripture are not just 2,000 years away from us. People are living out their faith this way in
the world today. And we don't know when that might come. We don't know where some of us here might be
called. Some of us might be called to go to hard places, places where there is persecution, places
where there are threats to our safety for following Christ. If that's the good work the
Lord has called us to, whether it's here, whether it's far away, will we be those who stand firm?
will we be those
who say I'm not going to be
distracted or deceived
will we stand firm
knowing our eternal hope
is in Christ's return
and so no matter
what we go through
in this life
and say Lord
I'm going to meet you
one day
I'm going to share
in your glory
it will all be worth it
can we stand together
as we respond
to the Lord here today